{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This country attempted to recreate a Six Day War strategy by launching Operation Chengiz Khan, disabling a rival’s air force in retaliation for their support of Mukti Bahini. Under Yahya Khan, this country launched Operation Searchlight to suppress the Awami League, a nationalist movement in a breakaway state. This country fought the Kargil War and frequently contests the region of Kashmir with its eastern neighbor. Bangladesh gained its independence from, for ten points, what northwestern neighbor of India?",
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote an opera about a man mentioned in Dante’s Inferno who impersonated Buoso Donati; that opera features the area “O mio babbino caro.” This composer of Gianni Schicchi [shee-kee] included Napoleon’s victory at the Battle of Marengo as a plot point in an opera whose title character sings “Vissi d’arte” and kills Baron Scarpia before throwing herself off Rome’s Castel Sant’Angelo. For ten points, name this composer of Tosca and an opera featuring Lieutenant Pinkerton and Cio-Cio San [cho-cho sahn], Madame Butterfly.",
      "answer": "Giacomo Puccini"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first public acknowledgement of the existence of these documents was a question presented by Fred Thompson to Alexander Butterfield on live TV. One of these documents includes a request to have L. Patrick Gray halt an investigation. Judge Sirica ordered a subpoena to obtain these documents, which were created using an Uher 5000. One of which was altered by Rosemary Woods and includes a mysterious 18-and-a-half minute gap. For ten points, name this type of document that was used as audio evidence in the Watergate scandal.",
      "answer": [
        "Richard Nixon’s White House tape recordings",
        "Watergate tape recordings before “Watergate” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In retirement, this man announced a series of articles limiting entertainment expenses and who can ride on palanquins, the “Laws of the Military Houses.” Late in life, this man lived in Sunpu Castle, where he had been held hostage as a child. This man abdicated the throne in favor of his son Hidetada [hi-day-tah-da]. This man’s victory at Osaka Castle brought an end to the rival Toyotomi clan. For ten points, name this warlord who established the last shogunate of Japan.",
      "answer": "Tokugawa Ieyasu"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man is the only MLB player with exactly 3,000 hits, a feat he achieved in the final at-bat of his career. After deciding to personally oversee relief efforts in Managua, this player boarded a previously damaged and overloaded DC-7 delivering aid to Nicaraguan earthquake victims; this man died on December 31, 1972 after that plane crashed off the coast of Puerto Rico. Major League Baseball’s award for off-field contributions and a bridge over the Allegheny River are named for, for ten points, what Hall of Fame outfielder for the Pittsburgh Pirates?",
      "answer": "Roberto Clemente Walker"
    },
    {
      "question": "A letter from Cicero describes this event as a “superb banquet” that he wished he had been a part of; that letter was written to Trebonius, who did take part. Servilius Casca almost revealed the timing of this event, which was later avenged at the Battle of Philippi. Calpurnia failed to deter the target of this event from appearing before the Senate. For ten points, name this event carried out on the Ides of March, 44 BC by Brutus, Cassius, and other conspirators against the dicatator of Rome.",
      "answer": "assassination or killing, stabbing, etc. of Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "A document calling for the creation of this legislative body was issued by a member of the House of Commons named Edwin Sandys. The first session of this body was presided over by George Yeardley. The cities of Henricus and Hundred Plantation were among those represented in this body. Vetoes could be issued by the governor overseeing this body, which also ceded power to its colony’s namesake company. For ten points, name this elected assembly established in 1619 in the Colony of Virginia.",
      "answer": "House of Burgesses"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting in the tomb of Puimre recorded one of these animals called “Nedjem,” or “sweet,” and the tomb painting “Fowling in the Marshes” shows one of these animals biting the wing of a bird. Herodotus described people shaving their eyebrows in mourning for these creatures, eighty thousand of which were found in Beni Hassan, and many of whom were entombed at Bubastis. Bast had the head of, for ten points, what domestic mammal whose names included mau and mju [mah-oo and “mew”] in ancient Egypt, where they were revered?",
      "answer": "domestic cat catus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Directly before he founded the New York Tribune, Horace Greeley published a newspaper of this name. Bob Dole’s 1996 presidential campaign controversially returned a $1,000 Republican donation from a group with this name; that group sued the U.S. in 2010 against the military’s “Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell” policy. A group of Republicans who advocate for LGBT rights is named after, for ten points, what type of frontier house, one of which served as Abraham Lincoln’s birthplace?",
      "answer": [
        "log cabins",
        "Log Cabin Republicans"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This agreement amended the ruling Inter caetera. Henry Harrisse claims that Jaime Ferrer devised the earliest suggested answer to the central question of this agreement. This agreement, which was authenticated in the city of Setubal, was agreed to a year after the Bulls of Donation were issued by Pope Alexander I. Pedro Cabral’s discovery of Brazil contributed to a boundary passing through South America in, for ten points, what 1494 agreement that established a meridian dividing New World holdings between Spain and Portugal?",
      "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Late in life, this woman may have taken on the name Porivo, as Charles Eastman discovered while trying to locate her remains. Despite being kidnapped by the Hidatsa people, this woman was able to reunite with her brother Cameahwait. This woman, who helped navigate obstacles like Bozeman Pass, was married to Toussaint Charbonneau; the couple was recruited at Fort Mandan to join the Corps of Discovery. For ten points, name this Shoshone woman who accompanied Lewis and Clark on their expedition.",
        "answer": [
          "Sacagawea",
          "Sakakawea"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lewis and Clark expedition met Sacagawea at Fort Mandan on the banks of this river, which they were following westward.",
        "answer": "Missouri River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Fabre d’Eglantine implicated a member of this group, Marie-Jean H´erault de Seychelles, in the Foreign Plot. Lazare Carnot was known as the “Organizer of Victory” for his role in this organization, whose actions were aided by the Law of Suspects. In Nivˆose Year 2, this organization arrested Jacques H´ebert and Georges Danton and sent them to the guillotine. For ten points, name this organization that was led by Maximilien Robespierre during the Reign of Terror.",
        "answer": "Committee of Public Safety or Comit´e de salut public"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the Committee’s first acts of political repression was purging 29 members of this political faction, named for a region in southwestern France and led by Jacques Brissot.",
        "answer": "Girondins"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John F. Hylan defeated a holder of this position who ran on a platform of universal military training; that man, John Purroy Mitchel, died after falling from a plane. Another holder of this position employed a man who used the CompStat program in his attempts to crack down on petty crime as an application of the “broken windows” theory. Bill Bratton served as police commissioner under Rudy Giuliani, who held this position during 9/11. For ten points, name this political office currently held by Bill de Blasio?",
        "answer": "Mayor of New York City or mayor of NYC"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "New York City implemented broken windows theory with a number of controversial policing practices, including this method of questioning and searching people on the street without full probable cause to arrest them.",
        "answer": [
          "stop-question-and-frisk searching",
          "Terry stop",
          "descriptive answers that use the words stop and frisk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The center of the Place [plahss] de la Concorde contains a monument from this country that was gifted to Louis-Philippe by Muhammad Ali Pasha. Jean Champollion [sham-pole-lee-ohn] became the Louvre’s curator of art from this country after he worked on deciphering a script found here. A military campaign to this country discovered a black stone engraved with the same inscription in Greek, Demotic script and hieroglyphs, the Rosetta Stone. For ten points, name this country where Napoleon Bonaparte was painted in front of the Sphinx and Pyramids.",
        "answer": "Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The obelisk in the Place de la Concorde was from this larger modern Egyptian city that contains the remains of several temples at Karnak and Thebes.",
        "answer": "Luxor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of this dynasty launched the Oei [oh-ay] Invasion, attempting to rid Tsushima Island of Japanese pirates. After this dynasty weathered 16th and 17th century invasions from the Manchus and the Japanese, its resulting isolationism earned it the name “the hermit kingdom.” During its waning years, this dynasty’s independence from China was secured by the Treaty of Shimonoseki. This dynasty’s most prominent ruler created an alphabetical system called hangul. For ten points, name this last ruling dynasty of Korea.",
        "answer": "Joseon dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Joseon ruler fought the Japanese on Tsushima and invented hangul.",
        "answer": "Sejong the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist proved that diamonds are produced of carbon by observing the production of carbon dioxide from a diamond exposed to sunlight. This man, who discovered that respiration is actually a combustion reaction, is considered to have written the first chemistry textbook, his Elementary Treatise on Chemistry; in that book, this man provided names for oxygen and hydrogen. The law of conservation of mass was discovered by, for ten points, what “father of modern chemistry,” a Frenchman who was guillotined in 1794?",
        "answer": "Antoine Lavoisier"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lavoisier was the first to show that this substance was elemental, rather than a compound of multiple elements. Charles Goodyear patented the process of vulcanization, the heating of rubber with this element to make it more durable.",
        "answer": [
          "sulfur",
          "S"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the site of the first usage of jamming chaff, where planes used “window” tinfoil strips to block radar during Operation Gomorrah. This country was the target of Operation Chastise, where Barnes Wallis developed an explosive that could jump on water to strike the Eder valley. Arthur Harris was accused of committing an “act of terror” by Winston Churchill after his planes set off a firestorm that killed 25,000 in this country’s region of Saxony. For ten points, name this country where Dresden was bombed during World War II.",
        "answer": "Nazi Germany"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned use of bouncing bombs was used to destroy these structures at Mohne and Edersee; the bombs became known as the “busters” of these structures.",
        "answer": "dams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An investigation at this location found that a design of Babcock and Wilcox had failed eleven times before it did so here. Roger Levin was among the authors of a medical article claiming that an event at this site did not cause increased incidence of thyroid cancer in Dauphin County. This location, named for its distance from the city of Middletown, lies on the Susquehanna River. A 1979 incident at this location was caused by a stuck valve at reactor 2. For ten points, name this American nuclear plant that experienced a partial meltdown.",
        "answer": [
          "Three Mile Island Nuclear Generating Station",
          "descriptive answers of a nuclear power plant at Three Mile Island"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Three Mile Island facility lies just downstream of this state capital on the Susquehanna River. This city filed for bankruptcy in 2011, due to an incinerator boondoggle and the first case of municipal securities fraud in American history.",
        "answer": "Harrisburg"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Muckraking",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Industry that was the subject of Upton Sinclair’s The Jungle?",
          "answer": "Meatpacking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muckraker who wrote The History of the Standard Oil Company.",
          "answer": "Ida Minerva Tarbell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Corrupt institution that was reformed with the passage of the 17th Amendment.",
          "answer": "United States Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Photographer who captured tenement life in his How the Other Half Lives.",
          "answer": "Jacob August Riis"
        },
        {
          "question": "“People’s Lawyer” who fought banks and became the first Jewish Supreme Court justice.",
          "answer": "Louis Dembitz Brandeis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female journalist who feigned insanity to expose the conditions inside asylums.",
          "answer": "Nellie Bly or Elizabeth Cochrane Seaman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Novelist whose book The Octopus was based on the Mussel Slough Tragedy.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Franklin “Frank” Norris Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Reporter who published The Shame of the Cities and who remarked “I have seen the future, and it works” about the early Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Lincoln Joseph Steffens"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Protestant Reformation",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Number of theses nailed to a church door by Martin Luther",
          "answer": "95 Theses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic Church’s practice of encouraging monetary donations in return for forgiveness from sin.",
          "answer": "indulgences"
        },
        {
          "question": "French theologian who continued the Reformation and has a branch of Protestantism named after him.",
          "answer": [
            "John Calvin",
            "Calvinism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss Reformation leader who introduced a new communion liturgy to replace the Mass.",
          "answer": "Huldrych Zwingli , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic council between 1545 and 1563 that began the Counter-Reformation.",
          "answer": "Council of Trent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who opposed Martin Luther’s ideas on reformation and eventually excommunicated him.",
          "answer": "Pope Leo X"
        },
        {
          "question": "English Reformation leader and Archbishop of Canterbury who assisted King Henry VIII in establishing the Anglican Church.",
          "answer": "Thomas Cranmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin Mass made mandatory in 1570 as part of the Counter-Reformation, which remained in use until 1962.",
          "answer": "Tridentine Mass"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Late Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Lover of Julius Caesar and Mark Antony who was the last ruler of her Greek-descended dynasty.",
          "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
        },
        {
          "question": "City founded by a namesake Macedonian conqueror that boasted a famous library and lighthouse.",
          "answer": "Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire that conquered Egypt from its capital at Nineveh before falling to the Neo-Babylonians",
          "answer": "Neo-Assyrian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty founded by a member of the diadochi that governed Egypt until it was conquered by the Romans",
          "answer": [
            "Ptolemaic dynasty",
            "Ptolemy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity supplied by Egypt to the Roman frumentarii, who were in charge of collecting this commodity before they became a secret police.",
          "answer": [
            "grain",
            "wheat and any equivalent thereof"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian ruler who succeeded Cyrus the Great and conquered Egypt in the 6th century BC.",
          "answer": "Cambyses II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Carthaginian navigator hired by Necho to colonize West Africa who may have circumnavigated the continent.",
          "answer": "Hanno the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nubian kingdom that briefly ruled Egypt under its kings Kashta and Piye. Its capital was Napata.",
          "answer": [
            "Kush",
            "Kerma"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this period, journalist Anthony Grey was imprisoned when the British legation was attacked in response to the suppression of leftist protests. A government based on the Paris Commune was founded during this period as part of the (20 pts)",
        "“January Storm.” The man who inspired this period later described it as “70 percent achievements and 30 percent mistakes.” The (10 pts)",
        "“Four Olds” were attacked during this period by student groups called the Red Guards. For ten points, name this period of unrest from 1966 to 1976 that targeted “counter-revolutionaries” in China."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A recording made at this location overwrote “I’m Sorry” by The Delfonics and other soul tunes. While at this location, Timothy Stoen signed an affidavit that he wasn’t the father of his son, which would later lead to a massive custody battle. This location was the site of (20 pts)",
        "“White Nights” simulated attacks, in which residents could either stay and fight or flee into the jungle. After investigating this location, Congressman Leo (10 pts)",
        "Ryan was killed at the nearby Port Kaituma air strip. The Peoples Temple ran, for ten points, what remote settlement in Guyana where cult members committed mass suicide in 1978?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jonestown",
        "Peoples Temple Agricultural Project"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a 2004 video, this man spoke of his experience fighting “tyrannical superpowers,” having “bled Russia for 10 years.” This man funded the Luxor Massacre and was inspired by damage sustained during the Siege of Beirut to plan another attack. (20 pts)",
        "Barack Obama told Leon Panetta that this man was a top priority. From the USS Carl Vinson, this man’s remains were (10 pts)",
        "buried at sea before the May 2, 2011 announcement of his death. Operation Neptune Spear targeted, for ten points, what leader of al-Qaeda and mastermind of the 9/11 terrorist attacks?"
      ],
      "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician ordered the expensive Napier expedition, which rescued hostages from Ethiopia’s Tewodros II. This man’s envoy, Louis Cavagnari, was killed during the second (20 pts)",
        "Anglo-Afghan War. This man’s support of the Ottoman Empire despite the Bulgarian Horrors was denounced in his opponent’s (10 pts)",
        "Midlothian Campaign. This man, who annexed the Zulu Kingdom, crowned Queen Victoria Empress of India. For ten points, name this Jewish Prime Minister, a conservative rival of William Gladstone in 19th century Britain."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At the onset of World War I, this character hands a German spy a copy of the book Practical Handbook of Bee Culture shortly before the spy’s arrest. This character adopts the alias “Pierrot” to post a newspaper advertisement that leads to (20 pts)",
        "Oberstein being arrested for the theft of the Bruce-Partington Plans. This character, who disguises himself as Altamont in “His (10 pts)",
        "Last Bow,” tracks his nemesis to Meiringen in Switzerland, where it is implied that this man and Moriarty tumble over the Reichenbach Falls. For ten points, name this detective created by Arthur Conan Doyle."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sherlock Holmes",
        "either name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family lost his re-election campaign as Governor of Rhode Island after he wiretapped a detective agency he had hired to investigate election fraud. During the sinking of the Lusitania, a member of this family gave his (20 pts)",
        "life vest to an infant despite the fact that he couldn’t swim. Holland McTyeire convinced a member of this family to fund a university. This family built Grand Central (10 pts)",
        "Station to bolster one of its businesses. TV journalist Anderson Cooper is a member of, for ten points, what American family whose patriarch, Cornelius, built a shipping empire? ANSWER:Vanderbiltfamily(acceptWilliamHenryVanderbiltIII;acceptAlfredGwynneVanderbilt Sr; accept Cornelius Vanderbilt; do not accept Cooper) (7) Thousands of “casket girls” emigrated to what is now this state, and their descendants are granted linguistic rights in this state’s 1974 Constitution. People subject to the Great Upheaval migrated to this state under (+) Henri Peyroux de la Coudreni`ere [en-REE pay-roo de la koo-dren-ee-air] after being forced out by British troops after the (*) Seven Years War. The Acadians migrated to, for ten points, what US state with strong French traditions like the Napoleonic Code and celebrations of Mardi Gras in New Orleans?"
      ],
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The long lasting effects of this event were studied in the 2006 TORCH report. The first responders to this event were formed into the “liquidators” and given medals of red drops of blood overlapped by (20 pts)",
        "alpha and beta particles. A facility in Forsmark, Sweden found evidence of this event the following day. This event created the (10 pts)",
        "Red Forest in a 30 kilometer exclusion zone around Pripyat. For ten points, name this 1986 disaster at a Soviet nuclear power plant."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chernobyl disaster",
        "any additional information relating to a meltdown and/or explosion at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant"
      ]
    }
  ]
}